THE LAST FANTASY | TLF HALFCD TeaM
字幕：破烂熊
校对、调轴、格式化：Obster-Y@github
仅供交流  严禁商用
专制国家
(“老大哥”是乔治·奥威尔所著《1984》中的独裁者,已成为专制的代名词)
摄制准备 一分钟后开始录制
Recording in one minute. Studio stand by.
我们会讨论削减政府的铺张浪费 对吗
We are going to talk about cuts in government extravagance, that's all the thing about, aren't we?
在结束国家资料库的相关问题后
We'll get to that if we've got time
如果还有时间我们就展开这个话题
after the National Database.
我可不觉得民众对资料库会感兴趣
I don't think people are really interested in the Database.
如此琐碎
It's so trivial.
摄像机就位
VT running.
-这是干吗?  -你的脸看上去太红了(pink有左倾之义)
- What's the matter? - You look a bit too pink.
脸红可不行，《每日电讯报》会怎么评论?
We can't have that, what would the Daily Telegraph say?
铺天盖地的“我们正在迈向一个极权国家?”
All those questions about "Are we creating a police state?"
-相信我 这点可以忽略  -得了吧 Jim，你了解我
- I trust we can do without those. - Come on, Jim, you know me.
我不会事先透露提问内容
I don't give out my questions in advance.
请都保持安静
Dead silence now, please.
10秒倒数
Ten seconds...
5 4 3 2 …
Five. Four. Three. Two...
晚上好
Good evening.
老大哥正在监视你吗? 更准确来说
Is Big Brother watching you? To be more precise,
你知不知道政府正在建立你的档案库
do you know the Government is building up a dossier on you.
还起了个听上去并无危害的名字
It's called by the harmless sounding name of
“国家综合资料库”
"National Integrated Database".
只需轻轻一按 任何公务员都能
It means that at the press of a button any civil servant
查阅你一生中的每个微小环节
can inspect just about every detail of your life
纳税 病史档案 失业次数
your tax, your medical record, periods of unemployment,
孩子的成绩 一应俱全
children's school records, and a lot. And that civil servant
而这个公务员可能恰好是你的邻居
may happen to be your next-door neighbour.
人们日益关注这一由计算机革命
Well recently there's been mounting concern over this powerful,
为政府带来的强有力的
even totalitarian weapon that the computer revolution
极权主义武器
has put into the Government's hand.
而挥舞这根大棒的人就是
And the man who wields the weapon is the Minister
行政事务大臣 下院议员James·Hacker阁下
for Administrative Affairs, the Right Honourable James Hacker MP.
大臣阁下 我们正为一个极权国家添砖加瓦吗
Now, Minister, are we laying the foundations of a police state?
我很高兴你问了这个问题
You know, I'm glad you asked me that question.
那么 大臣阁下 我们能得到答复吗
Well, Minister, could we have the answer?
当然可以 我正要回答 如果可以的话
Well, yes of course, I'm about to give it to you, if I may.
正如我所说 我很高兴你询问了这个问题
As I said, I'm glad you asked me that question.
因为
Because...
这个问题
it's a question
许多人在问
a lot of people are asking.
为什么呢?
And why?
因为大家愿闻其详
Because a lot of people want to know the answer to it.
就不转弯抹角了
And let's be quite clear about this without beating about the bush,
这个问题明摆着的事实就是
the plain fact of the matter is
它的确极其重要
that it's a very important question indeed
民众有权知道
and people have a right to know.
可是大臣阁下 我们还是没能闻其详
But Minister, we haven't yet had the answer.
不好意思 问题是什么?
I'm sorry, what was the question?
好吧 假设我在访谈中激怒了你
Now look, supposing I annoy you in this interview,
我怎么知道你不会回到办公室
how do I know you won't go back to your office,
轻轻一按 提出我的纳税记录
press a button and call up my tax records,
医疗记录 违归记录
my hospital records, my police record...
不会 不会
Oh no. No. No.
鲍勃 这不是我们国家的做事方式
Bob, you know as well as I do, that's not the way we do things in this country.
如果资料库不是用来核查民众 那是做什么用的呢?
Then what's the Database for if it's not to check up on people?
你看 这是个非常有趣的问题
You know, that's a very interesting question.
是用来保存信息
It's for storing information,
加速政府的运转
so as to speed up government business
我们就无需雇佣庞大数量的文案人员
so that we need not take on an enormous influx of clerical staff.
计算机是个大进步 是佳音
Computers are big business and are good news.
可是 大臣阁下 你要是把信息输入机器
But, Minister, if you put information into the machine,
你有朝一日就会从机器中读出这些信息
you'll eventually take information out of the machine.
这倒未必
Not necessarily.
这么说 你花了2千5百万英镑
So, you're going to spend 25 million pounds
收集信息却永远不用?
accumulating information and never use it?
不是 是的 不是
No. Yes. No.
会有安全措施的
Well, there will be safeguards.
例如?
Such as?
镜头拉近 他在躲闪鲍勃的问题
Close in on him, Two. Bob's got him on the run.
摄制 1分45
One minute 45, studio.
我们会关注所有的可能性
We'll be looking at a whole range of possibilities.
当然 这是件复杂并具有高科技的事情
And of course, it's a complex and highly technical matter.
冰冻三尺非一日之寒啊
Rome wasn't built in a day.
还在审核中
It's under review.
当然 这需要假以时日
And of course, these things take time.
大臣阁下 我是在与《改革》的前任编辑谈话
Minister, am I talking to the former editor of Reform
还是在和一个行政部门发言人呢?
or to a Civil Service spokesman?
我们还没就我提到的安全措施展开论述
We haven't talked about the safeguards I've already introduced.
例如 我新成立的政治监督办
And there's my new bureaucratic watchdog office, for instance.
看似不久我们会需要一大群看门狗了
It does look as if we'll need a whole pack of watchdogs before long.
还是十分感谢
But thank you very much.
好啦 请稍等片刻 我们要核对录影
Right, hold it there studio while we check the tape.
-如何?  -我想第一节进展的非常好
- How did it go? - Well, I thought... First class Very good indeed.
我似乎扯多了
I thought I waffled a bit.
不 大臣阁下 你“太极”打得好极了
Oh no, you stonewalled superbly, Minister.
去喝一杯?
Time for a drink?
安全措施展开论述
About the safeguards I've already introduced.
例如 我新成立的政治监督办
My new bureaucratic watchdog office, for instance.
看似不久我们会需要一大群看门狗了
Well Minister, It sounds as if we'll need a pack of watchdogs before very long.
还是十分感谢
But thank you very much.
下周的话题...
In next week's topic...
-我表现如何?  -大臣阁下 棒极了
- How was I? - Splendid, Minister.
非常庄重 非常得体
Very dignified. Very suitable.
是的 Humphrey爵士 祝贺你
Yes, Sir Humphrey, I congratulate you.
Jim现在训练有素
Jim is now perfectly house trained.
你告诉他什么他就说什么
He says and does exactly what you tell him.
-打断一下 Weasel先生  -是Weisel
- If you'll excuse me, Mr. Weasel. - Weisel.
你简直就成了行政部门的传声筒了
You just say everything the Civil Service programmes you to say.
你是人还是喉舌?
What are you, a man or a mouth?
Frank 非常有趣
Very amusing, Frank.
一个政治顾问理解这或许不易
It must be hard for a Political Advisor to understand this,
但我只是个公务员
but I am merely a Civil Servant,
无非是遵照主子的指示
I simply do as I am instructed by my master.
如果部长是个女人你怎么称呼她?
What happens when the Minister's a woman, what do you call her?
这的确有趣
Yes, that's rather interesting.
1947年那会
We sought an answer
Edith·Summerskill博士被委任为大臣阁下
when I was Principal Private Secretary and
我是首席私人秘书
Dr. Edith Summerskill,
我们想过解决的方法
as she then was, was appointed Minister in 1947.
我不太愿意称她为我的“情人”
I didn't quite like to refer to her as my Mistress.
-怎么解决的?  -还没有定论
- What was the answer? - We're still waiting for it.
还在审核 对吗 冰冻三尺非一日之寒
It's under review, is it? Rome wasn't built in a day. Is it Humphrey?
-这需要假以时日  -我真的得走了 大臣
- These things take time. - I really must be going, Minister.
-我也是  -您走之前 我想提醒您
- Me too. - Before you go Minister may I remind you
别忘了明早8点在Paddington饭店见
we meet tomorrow morning at Paddington at 8 o'clock?
-去哪?  -Swansea(威尔士南部港口城市) 大臣阁下
- Where are we going? - Swansea, Minister.
-Swansea？  -您将在市财政会议上发表演说
- Swansea? - Oh yes, You're addressing the Conference of Municipal Treasurers, the license and () in Swansea.
对
Oh, yes.
可是还有Newcastle(诺森伯兰郡首府)选举的致词
But Jim, You're due in Newcastle tomorrow night to address the by-election meeting.
-的确如此  -可您无法两个都去
- So I am. - Well you can't do both.
-我不能两个都去  -Jim，那不过是个公务野餐
- I can't do both, right? - Jim, that's a Civil Service junket.
-补缺选举才重要  -补缺选举很重要
- The by-election's important. - The by-election is important.
会议在几周前就添加在您的行程表中了 Swansea的人们期待您的到访
Er Minister, the Conference has been in your diary for some weeks. They do expect you to go to Swansea.
Newcastle的人们也期待您的到访
The central house expects you to go to Newcastle.
-Bernard，他怎么会有两个约会?  -Bernard，我怎么会有两个约会?
- Bernard how come he's double booked? - Bernard how come I'm double booked?
主要是Newcastle的事没人告诉我
Well, largely because, Minister, nobody told me about Newcastle.
-你为什么不告诉他，Frank?  -你为什么不?
- Why didn't you tell him, Frank? - Why didn't you?
我可记不住每件事
I can't remember everything.
Frank 我最好去Swansea
Frank, I think I'd better go to Swansea.
-决定了?  -是的 最终决定
- Is that a decision? - Yes, that's final.
首相希望您去Newcastle
The P.M. Expects you to go to Newcastle.
首相?
The P.M?
Bernard 我最好去Newcastle
I think I'd better go to Newcastle, Bernard.
-决定了 Jim?  -是的 最终决定
- Is that a decision, Jim? - Yes, that's final.
-那我回家了  -就这么定了?
- Now I'm going home. - Is that a decision?
是的 经过严肃思考
No, no, quite seriously...
我想你做了错误的决定
I think you've made the wrong decision, Minister.
您到访Swansea已经对外宣告
Your visit to Swansea's been announced, It's in the programme.
-您不能取消  -天哪
- You can't really get out of it. - Oh, Lord!
那找到一个让我从Swansea到Newcastle的途径
Well just find a way of getting me from Swansea to Newcastle.
汽车 火车 直升机 随便什么 我两个都去
Car, train, helicopter, anything. I'll have to do both.
现在我回家 这是最终决定
And now I'm going home, and that is final!
-最后的最后决定?  -不再更改
- Finally final? - Absolutely finally.
大臣阁下 如果您今晚能把这些盒子搞定的话
Er, minister, If you could be short to do all your boxes tonight.
全是M&A委员会的文件与信函 (M&A:兼并重组)
There's all the M&A Committee papers and all the letters we got before the weekend.
如果你做个乖孩子 保姆阿姨就会给你糖果奖励
And if you're a good boy, you'll nanny will give you a sweetie.
好
Good.
你好 亲爱的
Hello, darling.
-乔治 谢谢 晚安  -先生 晚安
- Thanks, George. Goodnight. - Goodnight, sir.
-你好 亲爱的  -你好
- Hello, darling. - Hello.
终于要离我而去了?
Leaving me at last?
你忘了明天是我们结婚的周年纪念?
It's our anniversary tomorrow, have you forgotten?
不会 当然没有忘
No, of course I haven't forgotten.
我们要去Paris 哦 老天
We're going to Paris. Oh, my God!
-你忘了  -不 我没有
- You had forgotten. - No, I hadn't.
没有 只是我... 我不能 我有两个...
No, it's just that I... I didn't... I'm double...
-我明天要去Swansea  -Swansea?
- I'm going to Swansea tomorrow. - Swansea?
还有Newcastle
And Newcastle.
我不想在周年纪念上那儿
I don't want to go Swansea and Newcastle for my anniversary.
不 没有你 我独自去
No. Not you. Just me.
-推掉  -不行
- Cancel them! - I can't.
你在做什么?
What are you doing?
取消 我们三个月前就决定了
Cancel them! We booked this three months ago.
-不行  -那我就自己去Paris
- I can't. - Then I'll go to Paris without you.
你好 Bernard 对 是我
Hello, Bernard... Yes, it's me...
听着 明天的行程不得不取消
Look, I'm going to have to cancel tomorrow.
Swansea和Newcastle
Swansea and Newcastle.
明天是我妻子的结婚周年纪念
It's my wife's wedding anniversary tomorrow...
也是你的
It's yours too!
对 实际上也是我的 对 就是这样
Yeah, and mine too actually. Yes, it is.
同时? 别傻了
What do you mean coincidence? Don't be silly.
总之 明天我去Paris 最终决定
Anyway, I'm going to Paris tomorrow and that's final.
是的 我是说过 但这次是最终的
Yes, I know I said that before, but this time it is final!
你要使出全身解数摆平
You'll just have to cope as best as you can, that's all.
没错
Yes?
对 很明确
Yes... definitely...
对
Yes...
明白了?
Is that clear?
好的
Right!
我们去Paris
We're going to Paris.
不 我要去Swansea和Newcastle
No, I'm going to Swansea and Newcastle.
-今晚在电视上看我?  -我倒是看到有个人像你
- See me on TV tonight? - I saw somebody who looked like you.
-这话的意思是?  -什么也不是
- What's that meant to mean? - Nothing.
Frank说我成了行政部门的喉舌
Frank Weisel says I've become a Civil Service mouthpiece.
-是啊  -“是啊”是什么意思?
- Yes. - What do you mean, yes?
-就是是啊  -你是说你同意?
- Well... yes. - You mean you agree?
-当然  -“当然”是什么意思?
- Of course. - What do you mean, of course?
你可以雇一个人去替你说这些话
I mean you could have hired and actor to say it all for you if he would said it better.
你为什么不直接用图章签名?
And why not just sign your letters with a rubber stamp?
或者让你的助理代劳
Or get an Assistant Principal to sign them for you.
反正就是他们写的
They write them anyway.
助理不能替代我签名
Assistant Principals do not write my letters!
行政次长可以
UnderSecretaries do that.
我放弃申辩了 大人
I rest my case, my lord.
-你认为我成了傀儡?  -是的 我认为是
- You don't think I've become a puppet? - Yes, I do.
也许你该让Piggy小姐做你的工作 她至少比你漂亮
Maybe you shoud get Miss Piggy to do your job. At least she's prettier.
我不知如何是好
I don't know what to do.
我被工作困住了
I'm just swamped by the work.
Annie 我很失落
Oh, Annie, I'm so depressed.
既然我们不去Paris
As we're not going to Paris,
至少今晚去街角的饭店吃顿安静的晚餐
let's at least go out for a quiet little dinner tonight at the [?] on the corner.
我不能
No, I can't.
Bernard要我今晚搞定这三个红盒子
Bernard's told me I have to get through three red boxes tonight.
你说什么呢 Bernard要求你?
What do you mean, Bernard's told you?
亲爱的 在《改革》做编辑的时候 你可不是这样的
Oh darling, When you edited "Reform" you were quite different.
你投入其中 告诉民众怎么做
You went in, you told people what to do,
按自己的意愿行事
and you got what you wanted!
你不先发制人就会被骑在头上
Either you get them by the throat or they get you by the throat!
那段日子你撕毁多少文章?
How many articles did you blue penciled and tear up in those days?
-几十篇  -那你现在撕毁过多少公文?
- Dozens. - And how many official papers have you torn up?
-这是不允许的  -不允许?
- I'm not allowed to! - Not allowed to?
亲爱的 你是大臣 可以为所欲为
Darling, you're the Minister, you can do anything you like.
不 Humphrey Frank是对的
No, Humphrey, I've decided that Frank was right.
Bob·McKenzie也是
And Bob McKenzie too.
国家数据库必须用其他的方式建立
The National Database has got to be organised differently.
是的 大臣阁下
Yes, Minister.
确保安全措施到位
We want all possible built in safeguards.
-是的 大臣阁下  -立刻
- Yes, Minister. - Right away.
“立刻”的确切意思是?
What precisely do you mean, right away?
就是马上执行
I mean right away.
懂了 你是指马上执行 大臣?
Oh I see, you mean right away, minister?
-Humphrey 确保到位  -好的 大臣阁下
- Got it in one, Humphrey. - Well, Minister...
或许我该提醒您 我们还尚在内阁成立初期
Perhaps I should remind you that we are still in the early months of this Government.
还有许多工作...
And there's an awful lot to get...
Humphrey 资料库的规章必须现在更改!
The Database rules have got to be changed. Now!
-可是您不能 大臣阁下  -不 我能 我是大臣
- But you can't, Minister. - Yes, I can, I'm the Minister.
是的 大臣阁下 您确实是
Yes, indeed you are, Minister.
而且是一位卓越的大臣阁下
And quite an excellent Ministerat that.
Humphrey 别奉承了
Nevermind the soft soap, Humphrey.
我要让所有公民都有权利查阅自己的档案
I want all citizens to have a right to see their own files
我要立法惩治未经许可的违规查阅
and I want legislation to make unauthorised access to personal files, illegal.
-很好 会被实施  -好极了
- Very well, Minister. It shall be done. - Good.
但要使这项公民权利法案生效
But the legislation necessary to give the public the right
将要通过极其复杂的诉讼
to take legal action is extremely complicated
并且耗费大量时间起草
and would take considerable time to draft,
宣传 颁布
promulgate and enact.
公民查阅自己的档案无需立法 对吗
Legislation isn't necessary for a citizen to see his own files, is it?
-是的  -那就从这开始
- No... - Then, we'll start with that.
我们将争取快点实施
Well, I suppose we could manage that slightly quicker, Minster
但还存在许多管理上的难题
but there's an awful lot of administrative problems as well.
Humphrey 先前对此肯定有过研究
Humphrey, this must have been examined before.
多年前资料库就在筹备中
I mean the Database has been in preparation for years. It hasn't just materialized over night
肯定就此展开过讨论
There must have been discussions about it.
-确实是  -达成的结论是?
- Yes, indeed, Minister. - What conclusions were reached?
Humphrey 达成的结论是?
Humphrey, what conclusions were reached?
我的前任对此抱何态度?
I mean, What did my predecessor want to do about it?
Humphrey 你能听到我说的吗?
Humphrey, can you hear me?
我必须守口如瓶
My lips are sealed.
再说一遍?
I beg your pardon?
我不能公开先前的计划 大臣阁下
I am not at liberty to reveal previous plans, Minister.
为什么不能?
Why not?
大臣阁下 您愿意把您在办公室的一言一行
Minister, Would you like everything that you said and done in the privicy of this office
都告知随后接任您职务的对手吗?
to be revealed subsequently to one of your opponents?
明白 不
I see. No.
我们不能给您对手政治弹药来对付您 反之亦然
We cannot give your opponents political ammunition against you. Nor vise versa.
可我的前任Tom·Sargent
But Tom Sargent was my predecessor.
与我是一个政治派系的 他不会介意的?
He wouldn't mind. It isn't a party political matter surely?
原则问题 不能公开
It's a matter of principle, Minister. It just wouldn't be...
我明白 不过我们又不是用来...
I see and we don't want to do anything that wouldn't be...
不行
No.
-打扰下 大臣阁下  -什么事 Bernard?
- Oh, excuse me, Minister. - Yes, Bernard?
小问题 大臣阁下
A slight problem, Minister.
由于反对的声浪
Because of the adverse...
您的访谈并没有获得一致的赞同
that is say tha not entirely favourable press reaction to your interview last night,
其他频道想让您上他们的节目
the other Channel wants you for their programme [?].
-拒绝  -不去?
Say no. - No?
-是的 不去  -好的 不去?
- Yes, no. - Yes no?
-是的 拒绝! 最终决定  -要是您这么想
- Yes, say no! That's final. - Well If that's what you want, Minister.
他们说了 就算您不露面 他们还会播出节目
They did say even if you didn't appear, they would go ahead with the item anyway
那时候可就没人替您维护了
and nobody would be there to state your case.
不去? 好吧 去
No? Okay, yes.
不去 好吧 去
No, okay, yes...
-我懂您的意思  -去
- Oh, I see what you mean. - Yes.
最后的最终意见?
Finally final?
Bernard 谢谢
Thank you, Bernard.
Humphrey  安全措施的问题我该怎么说?
Now, what am I going to tell them about safeguards. Humphrey?
你可提醒他们 大臣阁下
Well, perhaps you could remind them, Minister,
冰冻三尺非一日之寒
that Rome wasn't built in a day?
Tom
Tom.
-我的朋友  -介意我坐下吗?
- Oh, my dear fellow. - Mind if I join you?
当然不
No, of course not.
当反对党的滋味如何?
Well, how are you enjoying being in opposition?
执政的感觉如何?
How are you enjoying being in Government?
实际上并非如我期望那般 此刻就不是
Well, not as much as I expected, actually. Well, not at the moment.
Humphrey把你制服了?
Humphrey got you under control?
想做成点事情真难
It's so hard to get things done.
-你办成过什么事吗?  -几乎没有
- Did you manage to get things done? - Oh, almost nothing, oh boy.
我直到选举来临才摸透了他的战术
When I did cotton on to his technique through after been that a year, then there was the election.
-战术?  -拖延战术
- Technique? - Stalling technique.
-拖延战术?  -有五个阶段
- Stalling technique? - It comes in five stages.
首先 他会跟你说内阁新建 尚有许多事务要处理
First, he'll tell you there's lots of administration is very new and there are things to be getting on with.
-他今早就是这么多我说的  -当然了
- He told me that this morning. - Oh, Quite.
其次 如果你仍然坚持 他会这么说
Then, if you still persist, or whatever your idea is, he'll say something like
“好的 大臣阁下 意图很好
"Ah, yes, Minister, I quite appreciate the intention,
确实应该施行
certainly something ought to be done,
但你肯定这是实施它的正确方式?”
but are you sure this is the right way to achieve it?".
我应该记下来
I must make a note of this.
如果你还没有被唬住 他会改变立足点
Now, if you are still undeterred, he will shift his ground.
从告诉你如何做转向何时做
He will shift from telling you how to do it to when you should do it.
他会这么说
You know I mean, he'll say,
“大臣阁下 现在不是恰当的时机
"Now, Minister, this is not the right time,
出于各种原因”
for all sorts of reasons".
-大臣们就裹足不前了?  -多数如此
- [?] And Ministers settle for that? - Well, lots do.
如果你没有放弃
And if you don't,
他会说政策“实施起来困难重重”
well, he'll simply say that the policy "has run into difficulties".
-比方说?  -技术上 行政上 法律上
- Such as? - Technical, political, legal...
法律是最好的托词
Legal are the best sort of course.
他会使其听起来玄乎其玄
Because he can make those totally incomprehensible.
走运的话 这个战术会持续三年
And with any luck, this stalling technique will have lasted for about three years
到了最后阶段 他会告诉你
and you'll be known at the final stage when he says:
“大臣阁下 下一届大选近在咫尺
"Now, Minister We're getting very close to run up the next general election.
你能确保这项政策通过?”
Are you sure you can get this policy through?"
三年 怎么能拖了三年?
Three Years, How has it taken three years?
因为你不督促 Humphrey爵士是绝对什么也不会做的
Well because Sir Humphrey will do absolutely nothing in every stage unless you chase him.
而你偏偏还有一堆事情要做
And you've got far too much to do.
你瞧 他们称之为“创造的惰性”
You see, it's what they call "creative inertia".
你要设法通过什么政策?
What's the policy you're trying to get through anyway?
我试着让国家综合数据库
I'm trying to make this National Integrated Database
少些极权主义
a bit less of a Big Brother.
原来是这么回事
Oh, is that what it is?
-他告诉你这是新政策 对吧?  -是啊
- Now suppose he's told you it's all quite new, was he? - Well, yes.
我的朋友 这项法案我们耗了几年
My dear fellow, we spent years on that.
我们都备好了白皮书(政府报告)可惜大选来临
We had a White Paper [?] publication when they called the election.
这些我都做过
I've done it all.
-那些行政麻烦呢?  -全都解决了
- What about the administrative problems? - There aren't, I've solved them.
你没有看到任何先前的公文?
Did he tell you couldn't see any of the previous papers?
-是的  -不足为奇 都被他抹去了
-Yes. - No wonder. He's wiped the slate clean.
知道他的下一步会怎样吗?
Do you know what his next move's gonna be?
-不知道  -你拿到几个盒子?
- No. - How many red boxes have they giving you tonight?
-3个? 4个?  -5个
- Three? Four? - Five.
他有没有跟你说过不要太担心第5个?
Did he tell you not to worry too much about the fifth one?
-是的  -这就对了 我担保
- Yes. - Right. I'll take a bet.
你会在第5个盒子的底部 找到一个备忘录
You will find at the bottom of the fifth box a little memo
详细解释了为何
which explains exactly why
有关资料库的任何新举措必须暂缓
any new moves on the Database
如果你没能发现
must be delayed. Now If you don't find it,
他将无须盲目行事 但6个月后
he won't do another blind thing, but in six month's time
他会说他早已告知你
he'll say that he has told you all about it.
Tom 你从政多年 对公务员的花招真是无所不晓
Tom you were in office for years. You know all Civil Service tricks.
谈不上无所不晓 老兄 上百种花招而已
Not all, old boy. Just a few hundred.
那么你是如何让他们违心行事的?
And how do you defeat them, how do you make them do something they don't want to do?
亲爱的朋友 如果我知道就不会在野了
My dear fellow, if I knew that I wouldn't be in Opposition.
可我不理解 汤姆是反对党
But I don't get it. Tom's the opposition.
他为什么告诉你这些?
Why did he tell you all this?
-反对党并不表示敌对  -当然不 我犯糊涂了
- The Opposition aren't the opposition. - Of course not. Silly of me.
-他们只是这么称呼  -他们不过是在野的反对党
- They are called the oppositon. - They're the opposition in exile.
那些公务员才是在朝的反对党
The Civil Service are the Opposition in residence.
Tom说在第5个盒子的底部
Now then, bottom of the fifth box, Tom said.
但就算你知道也无能为力
But even if you know the techniques you can't really do anything.
无能为力?
Oh, can't I?
资料库相关的文件Tom都给我了
Tom's given me all his papers on the Database.
三年的价值
Three year's worth!
了不起
Marvellous!
找到了
Found it.
竟然被夹在一份长达80页的福利措施报告里
It had somehow slipped into the middle of an 80 page report on Welfare procedures.
“安全措施仍在讨论
"Safeguards still under discussion...
计划悬而未决
programme not finalised...
没有任何草率之举
nothing precipitate...
若无相左之指示 建议待发展再定夺”
failing instructions to the contrary, propose await developments".
显而易见
Typical!
-给Humphrey打电话 说你不同意  -我一早就会见他
- Why not ring Humphrey and tell him your disagree. - I'll see him first thing.
-现在就打给他  -现在可是凌晨2点
- Ring him now! - Now? It's two o'clock in the morning.
-他都要睡熟了  -要的就是这效果
- He'll be fell asleep. - Exactly!
Annie
Annie.
凭什么他安稳入睡你却仍在工作?
Why should he be asleep and you're still working?
他害你白白忙活 现在轮到你整整他
He's had you on the run for weeks. Now it's your turn.
我不能够这么做
I couldn't do that.
他电话多少?
What's his number?
何况材料在第5个盒子里 你根本无法早些看到
Anyway it was in the fifth box, you couldn't have got to it earlier, could you.
有道理
True.
喂?
Yes?
Humphrey 这么晚打扰你真不好意思
Humphrey, sorry to ring you so late.
我没破坏你晚餐的兴致吧?
I didn't interrupt you in the middle of dinner or anything, did I?
没有 晚餐早结束了
No, we finished dinner some while ago.
现在几点了?
Oh, good. What's the time?
凌晨两点
Er, two a.m.
-我的老天 出了什么大事?  -没有 一切正常
- Good God, what's the crisis? - No. No crisis.
我正在研究盒子
I'm going through my boxes,
而且我知道你肯定也还在鞠躬尽瘁
and I knew you'd still be hard at it.
对的 对的 埋头苦干
Oh, yes, yes, yes, yes. Nose to the grindstone.
那好 我刚看到资料库的文件
Well, I've just come across this Database paper.
您发现... 您看过了!
Oh, you've found... you've read it!
我得说这让我很不满
Thought I'd better tell you straight way I'm not happy with it.
你将有幸为此另寻出路
I knew you'll welcome an opportunity to work on something else right.
-不介意我打电话给你吧  -不 大臣阁下 一点也不
- You didn't mind my calling you? - No. Not at all Minister.
听到您的声音总是非常愉快
Always a pleasure to hear from you.
呀我忘记了，我还要跟他说要在内阁会议前把对策告诉我
Oh damn, I meant to tell him to see me about it before Cabinet.
现在别打给他
Don't ring him now.
是啊 现在是晚了点
No, You're right, it is a bit late.
让他先睡10分钟
Give him another ten minutes.
你最好速战速决
If you could be fairly quick, sir Humphrey.
-他10点要参加内阁会议  -我可以马上解决
- He does have Cabinet at 10. - I can be very quick.
Bernard “不行”是要对大臣说的最简洁的句子
Bernard, The word "No" is one of the shortest in the language, It's up to the Minister.
抱歉来晚了 今早有许多公文要读
Sorry to be so late. Lots of reading to do this morning.
Bernard 早安 谢谢 George
Good morning, Bernard. Thank you, George.
Humphrey 资料库的事
Now, Humphrey, the Database.
你起草了安全措施的计划书了吗
Have you drafted your proposed safeguards?
大臣阁下 我十分欣赏您的意图
Well, Minister, I quite appreciate your intention
而且非常认同安全措施的必要性
and fully agree that there is need for safeguards,
但是
but is this
-这是实施它的正确方式吗  -是我的方式
- the right way to achieve it? - Well, it's my way.
一个对上了
One.
无论如何 我主意已定
That's my decision, anyway.
出于各种因素现在不是恰当的时机
Well this is not really the time for all sorts of reasons.
两个对上了
Two.
现在正是时候
It's the perfect time.
安全措施应该紧跟系统的步伐
Safeguards should be developed alongside systems, not after them.
这是常识
That's common sense.
之前我们已经有过各种尝试 实施起来困难重重
Yes, but we have tried all this before, Minister. We ran into all sorts of difficulties.
三个了
Three.
比如?
Such as?
-例如技术上  -不 没问题
- Well, technical, for instance. - No. No problems.
我们可以实施与美国国务院
I have been doing a lot of research, We can use the same basic file interrogation programme
以及瑞典内政部一样的基本档案审核程序
as the U.S. State Dept. and the Swedish Ministry of the Interior.
这个不成问题
No problems there.
好吧 但行政上存在极大的麻烦问题
Yes, but there are also formidable administrative problems, Minister.
各部门都会受到影响
And all departments are affected.
-跨部门委员会...  -不不不 汉弗莱
- An interdepartmental committee... - No. No. No, Humphrey.
我想你会发现 现行的安全手续足以胜任
I think you'll find if you look into the existing security procedures are adequate.
只需简单地完善 还有吗?
This is simply an extension. Anything more?
-还有 大臣阁下  -例如法律上的问题?
- Well, yes, Minister. - Legal problems, for example?
-对 大臣阁下  -很好 很好
- Yes, Minister. - Good, good.
我们有法律上的权限吗?
Do we have the legal power?
我可以帮你解答 我们有
I'll answer that. We have.
工作人员的职权受到其协议的约束
All personnel affected are bound by their staff agreements anyway.
是的 但大臣阁下 这将需要额外配备公务员
Yes, but Minister, there will be a need for extra staffing.
你能让其在内阁和议会上通过吗
Are you sure you'll be able to get it through the cabinet and the parliamentary party?
是的 我确定可以 还有其它问题吗?
Yes, I'm quite sure. Anything further?
我看没了 我们可以着手去做了
I don't think so. Right! We can go ahead then.
你沉默不语了 Humphrey
You're very silent Humphrey.
大臣阁下 你似乎没意识到荆棘丛丛
Minister, You don't seem to realise the amount of work that's involved.
当然没有! 难道你曾调查过安全措施的问题?
No, Haven't you examined safeguards before?
我是说在以前的内阁里?
I mean under another government perhaps?
我似乎记得在议会上有过类似答辩
I seem to remember some written answers to parliamentary questions in the past.
首先我们经过协议这是不能...
Well, in the first place that I think we have agreed that question is not...
其次 即便有过调查
In the second place, if there had been investigations,
其实没有 因为没这个必要
which there haven't or not necessarily,
我没有权利去公开
or I am not at liberty to say whether there have,
有这么一个研究小组
there would have been a project team, which,
曾经存在过 我不是在下定论
had it existed, on which I cannot comment,
即便存在过也已经解散了
which would now have disbanded if it had existed
成员各自回到曾经的部门
and the members returned to do their original departments,
如果真的存在过这些成员的话
if indeed there had been any such members.
或者说某些情况下从没存在过
Or not as the case may be.
正是这样 大臣阁下
It's quite so, Minister.
Humphrey 我要安全措施立即实施
Humphrey, I want these safeguards on the Database made available immediately.
-大臣阁下 根本不可能  -可能
- Minister, it is not possible. - It is.
-不可能  -可能
- It isn't. - It is.
-不可能  -可能可能可能可能可能可能
- It isn't. - 'Tis, 'tis, 'tis, 'tis, 'tis, 'tis.
大臣阁下 只是提醒您 内阁会议在10点举行
Minster, Just to remind you, you have Cabinet at 10:00,
1点参加英美协会
then you are addressing the Anglo American Society at one,
傍晚接受“聚焦世界”的采访
and you got the "World in Focus" interview, this evening.
连个吃饭的空都没有?
Can't you get me out of the lunch?
很抱歉 大臣 已经对外通告过了
Well not really, Minister. It's been announced, It is in the programme.
我想想 我以为我...
I see... I suppose I...
-你刚说什么 Bernard?  -我们不能更改
- What's that you just said, Bernard? - I said we can't get out of it, Minister.
已经对外通告 已列入日程
It's been announced, it's in the programme.
Bernard 谢谢
Thank you, Bernard.
万分感谢
Thank you very much.
大臣阁下 出于什么?
For what, Minister?
出于一切 Bernard
For everything, Bernard.
聚焦世界
今晚在座的是行政事务大臣
Our Man on the Spot tonight is the Right Honourable Jim Hacker,
Jim·Hacker阁下
Minister of Administrative Affairs,
老大哥式计算机计划争论的中心人物
the man at the heart of the Big Brother computer controversy.
他正在接受Godfrey·Finch的访问
He's talking to Godfrey Finch.
大臣阁下
Minister,
如您所知 本周 民众对于众所周知的
as you know there's been an outcry this week
行政部门官僚正在为每个公民
about the dossier that the Civil Service bureaucracy
建立个人档案一事 大声疾呼表示不满
has apparently been building up on every citizen in this country.
现在传言事实并非如此 您个人的政策是
Now, it's rumoured that this is not in fact, your own policy,
您想为公民们实施安全措施
that you'd like to have safeguards for the individual citizen,
但在玩弄权术的政治舞台上
but that you are being totally frustrated at every stage
您遭到了滑铁卢
of the game by the Civil Service machine.
要知道 Godfrey
You know, Godfrey,
关于行政部门 颇多微词
there's a lot of nonsense talked about the Civil Service.
其实它是非凡而高效的专业机构
It's actually a marvellous, efficient, professional organisation,
充满活力 高速运转
capable of enormous energy and speed.
它汇集了许多有才干的无私奉献的人们
It's staffed by a lot of talented, dedicated people
正尽其所能帮助政府
who do everything in their power to help the Government
将政策转化为法律
make it's policies into law.
感谢您所做的广告 大臣阁下
Well, thank you for the commercial, Minister.
我们现在可以开始节目了吗?
Perhaps we can start the programme now?
实际上 行政部门和我
The fact of the matter is that the Civil Service and I
在整件事上的看法完全一致
are in complete accord over this whole business
我在此高兴地宣布
and I'm happy to announce that we're now ready
我们已准备好 将此提议公之于众
to put our proposals into publication.
事实上 今晚我可以说 从9月1日起
In fact, tonight I can say that from September the first,
英国的每位公民都绝对的权利
every citizen of the U.K. Will have the absolute right
查阅自己的私人档案 并核查
to inspect his personal file and check any information
任何他未曾向政府提供的信息
that he or she has ever supplied to the Government.
其次
Secondly,
没有大臣的许可 任何公务员将无权
no civil servant will be allowed to examine personal files
查阅其他部门的私人档案
from another department, without written authority from a Minister.
我在此宣布 下周将通过一项法案
And I shall be announcing in the House next week legislation
授权公民能向任何未经许可
enabling citizens to take legal action against any civil servant
查阅其档案的公务员提出诉讼
who gains unauthorised access to his file.
颇令人鼓舞 大臣阁下
Encouraging, Minister.
您为何不早日宣布 让人民不必为此担心?
Why did you not say so in the first place, and put people's minds at rest?
我不确信公务员能在最后期限完成 Godfrey
Thank you, I didn't believe that the Civil Service could meet our deadlines, Godfrey.
但他们让我深信能够做到
But they've convinced me that they can.
而且事实上 我的常务秘书
And, in fact, my Permanent Secretary
以他的名誉向我担保
has staked his reputation on it.
一旦未果 引咎辞职
And if not, heads will roll...
当然 秘书表率
Anyway, Assistant Heads.
大臣阁下 很感谢
Thank you very much, Minister.
-不能施行  -已经在电视上公布了
- It can't be done. - It's been announced on TV.
Bernard 瞧你让大臣都干了些什么
Bernard, what did you make of our Minister's performance?
我 我想这是将了您的军了 Humphrey爵士
Well, I... I think it's checkmate, Sir Humphrey.
Humphrey 昨晚在电视上看到我了吗?
See me on the box last night, Humphrey?
大臣阁下 当然看到了
Of course, Minister.
我表现如何? 不错?
How was I? Good?
精妙绝伦的演出
A most remarkable performance,
大臣阁下 如果我可以这么评价的话
Minister, if I may say so.
-你可以  -谢谢 大臣阁下
- You may, you may. - Thank you, Minister.
经过彻夜的辛苦工作
Well Minister, we have been working very hard all night,
我高兴地告诉您我们赶出了
and I'm happy to be able to tell you that we have come up
部分建议草案
with some draft proposals
可以让您在预定时间内
which would enable you to achieve your desired objectives
达成目标
by the stated dates.
干得漂亮 Humphrey
Well done. Humphrey
你看 我告诉全国你十分杰出 此话非虚
I told the nation how splendid you were and I was right.
-我对你非常有信心  -大臣阁下 的确如此
- I had every confidence in you. - Quite so, Minister.
你肯定经历了一个难以忘怀的夜晚
You must have had quite a night.
-是 大臣 难忘之夜!  -瞧瞧你的提案吧
- Yes, Minister, quite a night! - Let's see your proposals.
请过目
Here they are.
也来瞧瞧我的
And here are mine.
您也做了详细的建议书?
You have specific proposals too?
我确实做了
Oh, indeed I have.
汉弗莱 把你就安全设施所做的议案大声念出来
Now, Humphrey, you read out what you've got on safeguards,
我同样会念出我的 我们来对照下
and I'll read out what I've got and we'll see how they compare.
“个人资料 第一条:
"Personal data 1A:
安全措施必须以两项原则...
Safeguards must be applied with reference to...
为准绳
Two criteria.
有无必要与有无权利知道
The need to know and the right to know.
第一小项 有无必要知道
1A1. The need to know
仅将那些
only those officials...
被提供信息的公务员
for whom the information was submitted may be deemed,
初步视为有必要知道”
prime facie, to have a need to know."
汉弗莱 看来我们英雄所见略同
We seem to be of the same mind, Humphrey.
的确 大臣阁下
Indeed, Minister.
这个提案从哪儿得来的?
Where did those proposals come from?
大臣阁下?
Minister?
听到我的话了吗?
Can you hear me?
这个提案从哪儿得来的?
Where did those proposals come from?
汉弗莱 我得守口如瓶
Humphrey, my lips are sealed.